Morteza Baradaran

434-257-3579

 morteza@virginia.edu

 Homepage - in Linkedin

 github.com/Morteza1814

85 Engineer's Way, Rice Hall, Office:Rice 530 University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA 22904

Overview

My interests lie broadly in Computer Architecture, Bioinformatics, and Domain Specific Accelerators. I'm interested in exploring novel hardware and software techniques to enhance the performance, energy efficiency, and programmability of domain specific accelerators. I also have extensive experience in designing high-performance, energy-efficient embedded systems for core consumer products.

•Current research highlights: I am actively engaged in implementing a partial matching tool to align unidentified genomes within extensive Metagenomic datasets. To enhance this process, I am utilizing processing-in-memory accelerators, which greatly optimize the efficiency of large hash table processing during the filtering step. Furthermore, I am conducting a comprehensive comparison of the precision and performance of my technique with established state-of-the-art methods, including BWA. Notably, our tool not only improves the matching precision for partial matches, accommodating more edit distances, but also maintains comparable performance levels to BWA.

Notable Projects

Accelerating Unidentified Genome Partial Matching

Language: C/C++, Python

Goal: Accelerating Metagenomics Unidentified Genome Partial Matching using Processing in Memory

Links: https://github.com/Morteza1814/GenomePartialMatching

HashMem

Language: C/C++

Goal: Implementing a PIM-based Hashmap Accelerator Links: https://github.com/Morteza1814/HashMemCPU

Energy Consumption Analysis of Instruction Cache Prefetching

Language: C/C++, Framework: ChampSim, CACTI-7

Goal: Evaluating the energy consumption of instruction cache prefetching techniques

Banking Integrated Card Personalization System (IPS)

Language: C, C++, Java

Goal: Developing a Banking Card Personalization System Capable of Acquiring Customers' data and Personalizing it for Various Types of Banking Cards

Automatic Train Control Systems for Metro and Urban Railway

Language: C++

Goal: Developing and Analyzing Metro & Urban Railway Signalling and Telecommunication Systems (i.e., ATC, ATP, etc)

Self-Service Ticketing System of Tehran Metro and Bus Rapid Transit Routes

Language: C, C++

Goal: Developing Firmware, Memory Management, and File Management of the POS Terminals for Tehran's Subway Ticketing System

National Electronic Passport Operating System

Language: C++

Goal: Design and Implementation of OS Components for ARM7 Chip including Memory management, File System, and IO management

Education

University of Virginia, Charlottesville, USA Ph.D., Computer Science (Advisor: Prof. Kevin Skadron)	Sep. 2021 - Now (GPA: 3.95)
Sharif University of Technology, Tehran, Iran M.Sc., Computer Architecture (Advisor: Prof. H. Sarbazi-Azad)	Sep. 2010 - June 2012
Shahed University, Tehran, Iran B.Sc., Computer Engineering	Sep. 2006 - June 2010

Work Experience

Informatics Services Corp, Tehran, Iran Senior Software Development Engineer: Design and Development of Debit and Credit Card Personalization Systems	Sep. 2018 - Aug. 2021
TOSAN Group Corp, Tehran, Iran Lead Software Engineer: POS Development for ticketing system of Tehran Metro (QR, contactless cards)	June 2017 - Apr. 2018
MAHARAN Co, Tehran, Iran Software Engineer: Design & development of Automatic Train Control (ATC) and intermediate block system	May 2015 - Feb. 2017
National-ID Co, Tehran, Iran Hardware Specialist: Smart Card OS Design and Implementation including Memory management, File system, and I/O	Jul 2012 - Dec. 2013

Skills

Programming Languages/APIs:

• C/C++, Java, Python, Bash, Assembly Programming (x86), Verilog

Simulators and Analyzers:

• Gem5 Architectural Simulator, Multi2Sim, ChampSim, CACTI, Synopsys Synthesis

Benchmarking and Performance Analysis:

• SPEC Benchmarks, PARSEC Benchmarks

Industry Software Skills:

• KEIL, Jet Brain (IntelliJ IDEA, Youtrack), Microsoft SQL Server, OOP, DevOps, Design Patterns, JUnit, Maven, Sonarqube

Practical Skills:

• Embedded System Design, Software Development, Operating System Implementation, SOC Design

Research Experience

University of Virginia, Charlottesville, USA,

Sep. 2021 - Now

Graduate Research Assistant

Projects:

• Accelerating Unidentified Genome Partial Matching using Processing in Memory

Institute for Research in Fundamental Sciences (IPM), Tehran, Iran,

Sep. 2019 - Aug. 2021

Graduate Research Assistant

Projects:

• Energy Consumption Analysis of Instruction Cache Prefetching Methods

Sharif University of Technology, Tehran, Iran,

Sep. 2010 - June 2012

Graduate Research Assistant

Projects:

• Obtaining Better Processor Performance through a Shared Structure between Cache and BTB

Publications

- A. Shekar, Morteza Baradaran, S. Tajdari, and K. Skadron, "HashMem: PIM-based Hashmap Accelerator," in Fifth International Workshop on Domain-Specific System Architecture (DOSSA-5), 2023
- M. Baradaran, A. Ansari, M. Sadrosadati, and H. Sarbazi-Azad, "Energy Consumption Analysis of Instruction Cache Prefetching," in Submission
- M. Baradaran and M. Zarei, "Theory of Automata and Machine Language," in National Library of Iran, ISBN 978-600-6927-22-0, 2012-2013

Courses

2041363	
CS6501: Hardware Accelerators University of Virginia	Spring 2023
CS6501: Geometry of Data University of Virginia	Fall 2022
CS6316: Machine Learning University of Virginia	Spring 2022
CS6160: Theory of Computation University of Virginia	Fall 2021
CS6354: Computer Architecture University of Virginia	Fall 2021

Teaching Experience

Teaching Assistant, CS4414: Undergraduate Operating System	Fall 2022
University of Virginia	

References

Two references will be made available upon request.